<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Athenian Society unvaild: or, Their ignorance and envious abusing of the Quakers detected and reprehended</title>
            <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186898</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529381</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06714)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2782:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Athenian Society unvaild: or, Their ignorance and envious abusing of the Quakers detected and reprehended</title>
                  <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
                  <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott in George-yard in Lombard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Wyeth by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Printed in two columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</term>
               <term>Athenian Society (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Athenian Society Unvaild: Or, their Ignorance and Envious Abuſing of the QUAKERS Detected and Reprehended.</head>
            <p>THE Prediction of the Bleſſed Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>All that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer Perſecution,</hi> has been the perpetual Experience of the Church of Chriſt in all Ages; only with this variation, that their Sufferings have been ſometimes after one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſometimes after another; one while Life, another Liberty; and very frequently Eſtates have been the Prizes that an innocent and harmleſs Life have coſt their Owners: The Truth hereof is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, not only by Hiſtory very Ancient, but alſo by ſome ſo very Modern, that it is not yet paſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. But when all theſe in good meaſure have, by God's Providence and a Government's Favour, been ſtopped, then the ſame Spirit, frequently in the ſame Members, and ſometimes in others, hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to blacken and miſrepreſent thoſe they could not deſtroy under the Pretext of Law. This is the preſent Caſe; it is but a little while ſince, that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Eſtate were the common Rates which we call'd Quakers (with many others) were made to compound at (if I may ſo ſpeak) for our Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Conſcientious Scruples. But the mildneſs and gentleneſs of the preſent Government, has ſo ſignally gone beyond that of ſome of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, that they have <hi>not only</hi> recommended theſe excellent Qualities by <hi>their particular Example, but alſo by the</hi> Authority of a Law, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by us, with true Gratitude and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. Now the Advantage of ſo Noble an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, one might think ſhould have been ſufficient, if not to ſweeten, yet to chill the moſt virulent Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and more eſpecially yours, who call your ſelves the <hi>Athenian Society;</hi> and have made ſo many Offers at a Reformation, by the pubick Pretences you have made, to encourage ſome and adviſe all to the furtherance of it: Theſe, 'tis true, have been your Pretenſions, but your Practice is no other than the Tranſcript of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Preface to the ſecond Volume.</note> Jeſuits Maxim; who you ſay were they, that by their Diſguiſes and falſe Pretences were the firſt Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the many unhappy Differences that are now among us, both in Church and State. Now what is odious in them, can it be lovely in you? Or what is againſt the Peace of Government in them, can it be otherwiſe in you? Surely no: For Crimes loſe not their Nature when they only change their Agent, nor is Satan at all the more Holy for being in an <hi>Athenian,</hi> or in one called a Chriſtian: The Truth of this you have ſufficiently evinced by the Falſhoods and Abuſes which you have ſo liberally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed both upon Communities and particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And yet you are the Men, who at your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance by this Name, promis'd to uſe in your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Deſign, much Chriſtian Candor and Modeſty; and not to
<note n="*" place="margin">Preface to the ſecond Volume.</note> widen the Breaches, but to avoid either Practices or Diſputes that might tend thereto: And further, that you would anſwer no obſcene Queſtions, nor any whoſe Anſwer ſhould be an Abuſe to particular Perſons: With more to the ſame purpoſe, which I could here recite, were it as neceſſary as it is eaſie. But I ſhall here paſs it over, as well as your other Contradictions and Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, of which we have generally notice once a Week by the <hi>London Mercury;</hi> for my Deſign is, herein chiefly to inſtance in thoſe Anſwers of Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which were the cauſe of the Letter I ſent you, (which I ſhall ſet down anon) to which, tho' you promis'd an Anſwer, yet have not given one, unleſs Queries and Impertinency may deſerve that Name; by detecting your Falſhood and Lies, and alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning <hi>John Whitehead,</hi> whom by Name you have abuſed in your Buffoonry. But I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that in defiance of your Rules, in breach of your pretended Charity, and contrary to Morality and to true Chriſtianity, you have ſeemed glad of an opportunity to be abuſive towards us in particular, as will plainly enough appear, by your Anſwer to a Queſtion in <hi>Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>N.</hi> 8. q. 6. <hi>Whether it be lawful for a Chriſtian to Swear?</hi> To which you, not content to deliver your Anſwer in the Affirmative only, have ſtigmatiz'd all as ſilly Enthuſiaſts who believe the contrary. Now as this Anſwer of yours did cauſe, ſo your Promiſe that you would fairly Anſwer any Objections that were made to your Anſwers, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the ſending of a Letter to you ſoon after; wherein among other Things, were the three fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Queries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether ſince the very end of Chriſt's coming into the World</hi> (as is teſtified) <hi>was to take away Sin and finiſh Tranſgreſſion, he did not thereby ſuperſede the very uſe of all Oaths?</hi> 2. <hi>Whether if Men did cooperate with the Aſſiſtance that Christ Jeſus lends, and obey the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts he has given, they might not thereby attain the end of his coming?</hi> 3. <hi>Whether there is any poſitive Command in the Goſpel, enforced by words more comprehenſive, full poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and pertinent, than this of</hi> Swear not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179287:2"/>
            <p> To theſe you have not returned any Anſwer, as by your fore-mentioned promiſe you were obliged, but ſtill proceed further to abuſe and belie us, in ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as your own Eyes and Ears, if you ever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed them to read or hear our Principles from our ſelves, muſt needs convince you of (for you ſay you have uſed them herein:) From whence the Inference is very eaſy, that your Diſeaſe is Malice, becauſe your Aſſertions are directly contradictory to what has been at all times Spoken and Written by our Friends: But if you have not read or heard from our ſelves, what you have aſſerted to be our Belief, then what Abatements are to be made from the Malice of your Charge, muſt be added to the Impudence of it, in that you are of thoſe, who ſaid, <hi>Report, and we will Report it;</hi> which ſhews you to be neither more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian nor leſs Wicked; this will beſt appear by the Charge it ſelf. <q>Where in <hi>Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>N.</hi> 23. q. 4. you affirm the Quaker's Opinions to be dangerous and deteſtable (as indeed they were, were it true, that you afterwards affirm) that they ſpeak contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly of the Bible, and will by no means allow it to be God's Word; that they have turned the moſt Sacred Truths therein contain'd, into jejune Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory; that they ſpeak not very Honourably of our Saviour, deny the Trinity, and many, if not all, embrace the other <hi>Socinian</hi> Dream, of the <hi>Soul's Sleeping till the Reſurrection:</hi> And afterwards in <hi>Vol.</hi> 4. <hi>N.</hi> 30. q. 1. The Quakers have been e're ſince their riſe, look'd upon as the Jeſuits, By-Blows of the Jeſuit; that they deny the plenary Satisfaction of Chriſt, and reſt on their own Merits; that Fanaticiſm, Enthuſiaſm and Infidelity together, make up the Creed of the Quaker, they being a Compendium of almoſt all ſorts of Hereſies; who deny the Satisfaction and Divinity of Chriſt, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Humanity; nay, deny Angels, Spirits, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell, and the Exiſtence of Souls after Death.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here is the Complex of your Lies and Slanders, freed from the profound Nonſenſe and palpable Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, wherewith you have formally interlarded each of the above cited places; but of each I ſhall give an Inſtance. Firſt in the 23. <hi>N.</hi> q. 4. where you ſay—<hi>But if there be any of 'em who have left their firſt Principles, and are degenerated into Chriſtianity.</hi> What! think you Chriſtianity to be worſe than our Principles? For Degeneracy is, I think, to go from better to worſe; or if this be to Frolick with Words, it's a very odd way of doing it. Of your palpable Ignorance, let this be an Inſtance, where, in <hi>N.</hi> 30. q. 1. you ask, <hi>How they have the Face to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to what they never had, Chriſtianity, when they were never Christen'd?</hi> Now, if by Chriſtning you mean Sprinkling a Face with Water, I am ſure it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to that of the Apoſtle, who ſignifies, <hi>That true and ſaving Chriſtianity conſists, in having the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſprinkled from dead Works, to ſerve the Living God:</hi> Which cannot be purged by any ſuch external Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but only and alone by the Spirit of God in Man. By this time, I ſuppoſe, it will be thought ſufficiently reaſonable that we clear our ſelves, or that you ſhould prove theſe your Aſſertions, which that you might do the laſt, was the occaſion oth' Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which (in that you call your Anſwer, in <hi>V.</hi> 5. <hi>N.</hi> 29. and which I ſhall conſider anon) you call an angry one, and not agreeable to the Precept of <hi>Turning the other Cheek;</hi> to which I muſt tell you, that it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known to have been our conſtant Practice, to bear the Smitings, the Buffetings, the Waſtings and the Plunderings, which Men of your Spirit and Temper have inflicted upon us under the pretext of Laws, whilſt in uſe. Under all which Sufferings, God did by the Sheddings forth of his Spirit, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our Spirits, that we can ſay in Truth, we took joyfully the Spoil of our Goods and Impriſonment of our Bodies, for his Name ſake, and can alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them that did it; only deſiring for the worſt of them, as for you, That you may come to ſee the Evil you have done by theſe your Lies and Scandals, and turn from them by a ſincere and hearty Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; that ſo your Sins may be forgiven, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the Lord's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. But notwithſtanding all this, ſhould we be ſilent to theſe your Lies, it might be conſtrued a joyning with you againſt that <hi>Holy Truth,</hi> of which we are Profeſſors, which we cannot do; but muſt herein clear it from your Calumnies. And the <hi>Jews</hi> might have told <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt he was angry, when he calls them a <hi>Generation of Vipers:</hi> The like they might have told Holy <hi>Stephen,</hi> when in <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51, 52. he calls them, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed in Hearts and Ears, Reſiſters of the Holy Ghoſt, Perſecutors of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Betrayers and Murtherers of the Just One.</hi> They both ſpeak Truth, and its warmneſs was juſtified by its occaſion. And now to ſhew that the warmneſs of this Letter, bears no proportion to the occaſion you have given, and that I have not requited you with Vineger for your Gall, I ſhall here give the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py thereof; but without your frothy and abuſive Parentheſes: Which is as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Copy of the Letter I ſent them.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Athenians,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT, and ſince, your appearing in the World (by this Name) your repeated Proteſtations of Chriſtian Candor and Modeſty, in anſwering ſuch Queſtions, as were fit to be anſwered, and total Silence in ſuch as were not; did make the Ingenuous of either Sex (however di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd) willing to further what might be of Service to the Publick: But your notorious Prevarications have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſhewn, that what was intended for your Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and others Service, you have only made uſe of as a Ladder to climb higher than others, whereby you might have the hateful opportunity of abuſing what, and whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever agrees not with you; and that by Aſperſions ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably groſs and falſe, that it needs not the Judgment of an <hi>Athenian</hi> to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvail you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The preſent Eaſe and Felicity which we, called Quakers, do with others, find under the happy Influence of a mild and generous Government (which Happineſs, we do with all Duty and Gratitude thankfully acknowledg and remember) has ſo far buried the late Diſtractions, Waſte and Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, that they are hardly now to be met with but in Hiſtory. And that this Peace and this Felicity might be perpetual, the Wiſdom of the Nation has been ſo <hi>Latitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarian</hi> (to uſe your diſdainful Expreſſion) that among other Things, in an Act for that very purpoſe made, they have framed what they there Call, and what truly is, a Chriſtian Profeſſion or Confeſſion; the Owners and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers of which, as they are the King and Queens Lieg-Subjects, ſo they are Chriſtians in Belief, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all your Buffoonry and wilful Lies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſhall only at preſent enumerate the Heads of your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scandals and Abuſes, which in your Preface to the <hi>3. Volume,</hi> you ſay you took ſo much Pleaſure in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing: The firſt is <hi>Vol. 3. N. 8. q. 6.</hi> where you tax the paying of Obedience to a poſitive Command of Christ with Enthuſiaſm; but this being Language too kind, you do with the next opportunity, in <hi>N. 23. q. 4.</hi> of the ſame
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179287:3"/>Volume, aſſert upon your own Knowledg, our believing a number of portentous and monstrous Opinions, you there number up, and which here we do utterly deny, and ever did, declaring ſuch your Aſſertion to be Falſe, Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and Malitious; hereby requiring you to make your Aſſertions good, or to be accounted, what you truly are, that is, the worſt of Incendiaries; which Title, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the World, does peculiarly belong to you, you have in another of your Mercuries,<hi>Vol. 4. N. 30. q. 1.</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to draw a Parallel between Quaker and Papiſt; but with ſuch known Falſhood, that there is now hardly any Perſon, who pretends to much leſs Reading than your witty ſelves, but knows it to be no other than a Malitious Lye; which plainly ſhews, that notwithſtanding the noiſy Offers, which you in your Mercuries make at a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, your ſelves have not advanced the firſt Step to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it: And in the last-mentioned Queſtion, where you pretend to conſider them aſunder, you have done it ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learnedly, as well as falſly, that perhaps it needs not the ſtrength of a Champion to foil you, who have fallen from the forms of Civility as well as Chriſtanity, in that you have falſly belyed and accuſed your Neighbours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You are not to ſuppoſe that this comes in the manner of a Question, which you may not think fit to Anſwer; for it is hereby declared, That if you do not, within ſome reaſonable time, give the World clear Proofs of your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, in the Places and Anſwers above-noted, you ſhall be expoſed, and your Falſhood and Baſeneſs detected, not only by the <hi>Verbatim</hi> hereof in Print, but by a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Anſwer to each of your many Lies; I call them by this Name, which you affirm to be the detestable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which we hold, and indeed do not, nor never did.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Decemb. 22. 1691.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <byline>By one who is in Scorn called a QUAKER.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this it appears that its end is, either that you would prove your Aſſertions or retract them; but inſtead of doing either, in that which you call your Anſwer, you have only ſhewn a little more ill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a great deal of Impertinency, in running ſo very wide from the Mark as you have done; by making your fooliſh and falſe Harangues, without proving any thing; and all this with a deſign (to uſe your own words) to preſerve thoſe of your Communion, by ſhewing them what Principles you ſay we really hold. But if you have no better Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives, than theſe palpable Lies, you need not wonder that People, coming to the Knowledg of that ſelf evident Principle, of the Light, Grace or Spirit of God in their own Hearts, do then leave you and your refuge. And here I muſt obſerve, that to evade the proving your Charges and to prevent any cloſer Anſwer, you endeavour to amuſe the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and frighten us, by asking 10 Queſtions (if at leaſt they all deſerve that Name) in which you think there is ſo much Acumen, that they touch us to the quick; and all theſe to be anſwered Catagorically, or elſe the worſt is to be taken <hi>pro Confeſſo.</hi> Now to Queſtions, on which ſo great ſtreſs is laid, the Reader will very naturally ſuppoſe, they ought to be very pertinent and very weighty; but I muſt inform him that in this preſent caſe it's far otherwiſe, as will appear plain enough by repeating them; and which are as follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether they all generally own the Scriptures to be the Word of God?</hi> 2. <hi>Whether they own Jeſus Chriſt to have been God equal with the Father from all Eternity?</hi> 3. <hi>Whether they own the Holy Spirit to be God; and that in the Holy Trinity, there are three Perſons and one God bleſſed for evermore?</hi> 4. <hi>Whether they hold their boasted Light within to be this very third Perſon, or only their own natural Reaſon?</hi> 5. <hi>Whether they partake of either of the Sacraments in their Congregations; or whether they do not abſolutely neglect both Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord?</hi> 6. <hi>Whether they believe Angels, or any Immaterial Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits beſides the Soul of Man?</hi> 7. <hi>Whether they believe the Existence of the Soul after Death and Reſurrection of the Body, and Reunion of the Soul thereunto at the day of Judgment?</hi> (Now the terrible ones) 8. <hi>Who was your firſt Founder?</hi> 9. <hi>Did they Quake and Tremble or no when they first came into</hi> England, <hi>and the reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?</hi> 10. <hi>Where may we find their Creed or an Act of their Religion? And whether it is not altered in ſeveral particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſince their Riſe, tho' but of ſo few Years standing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are what you vainly and falſly ſet to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Chriſtianity by, but they cannot do it; becauſe ſome of them are Antiſcriptural (which yet you call your Rule) and others ſo ridiculous that they could not be asked, by a Man truly Chriſtian; ſo that if I ſhould not refer you to any Anſwer to theſe (for you would not have it now done <hi>de Novo,</hi> but by the Teſtimony of our Authentick Writers) your mighty Threaten would ſignifie nothing; for it remains for you to prove your Aſſertions, they being denyed by us; and tho' at pleaſure you throw by your own Rules, yet you muſt not pretend to do ſo, by the continual Rules of Debate and Diſcourſe. But the trouble hereof being as ſmall, as your expectation can be great, I ſhall for this once do it; when I have firſt acquainted you, That tho' you pretend to be more <hi>Athenian</hi> than the Senate of the Nation; yet it will hardly become you to pretend to be more Chriſtian than it: And if ſo; then, ſince Malice or ſome ſuch Humour has ſpoiled your Memory, I will take leave to acquaint you, that in an Act made 1689. Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>An Act for exempting their Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> &amp;c. there is ſomething which upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Holy Writ, as well as their own, is call'd a Chriſtian Belief, and was made on purpoſe for us, call'd Quakers, as by the Act appears; and is as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Profeſs Faith in God the Father, and Jeſus Chriſt his Eternal Son the true God, and in the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit one God bleſſed for evermore; and do acknowledg the Holy Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament to be given by Divine Inſpiration.</hi>
               </hi> This having been at all times (as it now is) our hearty Belief, you might have ſpared your three firſt Queries, which are not ſo Scriptural: To your fourth query, read <hi>Geo. Keith</hi> of <hi>Immediate Revelation not Ceaſed:</hi> To your ſixth and ſeventh, read <hi>Sam. Fiſher,</hi> in a Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>[Some certain hidden Spiritual Verities revealed:]</hi> And likewiſe for Anſwer to many of them, you may read <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> written by <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> and <hi>Will. Penn:</hi> And laſtly, both to theſe and the reſt, read <hi>Rob. Barclay,</hi> in his <hi>Apology for the true Chriſtian Divinity,</hi> in which you will find a diſtinct Account of our Principles, and that they are conſonant to Holy Writ, right Reaſon and pure Antiquity; for which reaſon it is, that our Principles are not chang'd nor indeed can be, they being preſerv'd by the Spirit of God in us, with which there is no Variableneſs nor Shadow of turning: And many more (would I be prolix) I could number up, but here being enough, and more than is needful in this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſhall ſtop. Now in theſe cited Authentick Writings you may find (as I have ſaid) not only more than enough to Anſwer your Queries, but alſo the Truths therein contained, ſo clearly delivered, that were ye honeſt enough to confeſs it, you would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179287:4"/>ſay there is much leſs of the Jeſuit in them, than there appears to be of their Nature in you, as is evident by your groſs Lies and Abuſes; which that I may not forget and you run from, by that Evaſion which you pretended to fear in us; I ſhall here put you in mind, That whatſoever you ſhall ſay hereafter, cannot be look'd upon to have any Weight, unleſs you either prove or retract theſe your bold Affirmo's; which are hereby returned upon you as your Lies, <hi>viz.</hi> You affirm, 1. <hi>That the Quakers reſt on their own Merits.</hi> 2. <hi>That they deny Heaven, Hell, Angels and Spirits.</hi> 3. <hi>That they believe the Soul to ſleep in the Grave until the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> 4. <hi>That they deny the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt.</hi> 5. <hi>That they deny the Scriptures to be the Word of God (or given by Divine Inſpiration.) And</hi> 6. <hi>that Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm, Enthuſiaſm and Infidelity, do make up the Quaker's Creed.</hi> If you pretend to prove them, it is expected that you do it from our Selves, or our own Writings; but if you cannot, let it hereby appear how fairly you have merited the Title of Incendiaries, which yet you're loath to own; but it being your due, you muſt be ſo accounted, in that you're Diſturbers of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace, which never had more mortal Enemies, than thoſe, who under the mask of Religion have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to foment civil Broils, by the mutual Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which their falſe and noiſy Clamours have too frequently procured. But in this Inſtance, the Peace is thus far ſecured, that if you do neither retract, nor prove your Aſſertions, your Abuſes being caſt upon a People, who return not Evil for Evil, are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bound to return an Anſwer to every impertinent Scrible, this not being written either from Humour or mercenary Intereſt, is not deſign'd to be repeated whereby to trouble my ſelf or others, who will hereby ſufficiently underſtand your baſeneſs, in your general Lies and Abuſes, as now they ſhall your abuſive handling of <hi>John Whitehead,</hi> who is belyed by your Queriſt (if at leaſt it were not your ſelves) and both abuſed and belyed by you in <hi>Vol.</hi> 4. <hi>N.</hi> 30. q. 2.</p>
            <p>Now here had been a fit opportunity to have put in practice that Rule of yours, which was, not to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer any Queſtion, whoſe Anſwer might be an abuſe to particular Perſons. But you, conſidering it was a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, did diſpence with it, tho you expoſed your ſelves by rallying upon a Lie, in which there is ſo much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenity, that it puts me in mind of a certain Altar which was at <hi>Athens,</hi> erected to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rous Archaeologiae Atticae, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>Injury and Impudence,</hi> and upon which I find not only the Ancient, but alſo the Modern <hi>Athenians,</hi> do ſometimes Sacrifice, as will ſufficiently appear by the fulſom Stuff with which the laſt cited Anſwer is fill'd. But firſt, your Query is falſe in fact, and <hi>John White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> did never ſo boaſt, as that affirms, of his Fatneſs; nor was he ever forced when in Priſon, to feed on Bread and Water, nor was he ever 3 yards about the Waſte, nor is his Wife near that ſize: Now before you went thus to rally, and be merry with the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Family, ſure you ſhould have taken as good Caution not to have been deceived, as you have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times required to the Atteſtation of an Experiment in Art, or Caſualty in Nature, in which you have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times required more than the Name of the Relator; which if you cannot produce in this Inſtance, let it be ſuppoſed your ſelves were the Queriſt, and ſo guilty both of the Lie and the Abuſe; which being ſo particular, take <hi>John Whitehead</hi>'s Anſwer as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A few Queſtions for Anſwer, to the Authors of a Scandalous, Impertinent Paper, Entituled, <hi>The Athenian Mercury, Vol.</hi> 4. <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>WHether ſuch Perſons as by their Words or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſay, <hi>Come let us Smite him or them with the Tongue, Report and we will Report it,</hi> do not as much as in them lies, indeavour to ſtir up a new Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution? And whether herein they do not ſymbolize with the worſt Heathens and Papiſts, who uſed to cloath the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtians in ugly Shapes, and painted Devils upon them, that they might be the readilier devoured by wild Beaſts, and burnt to Death by the wicked Hands of cruel Men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether great blindneſs of Mind hath not happen'd to ſuch Men, as do look upon the People of God (in ſcorn cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers, who are at the greateſt diſtance from Popery of any People in the World, profeſſing Chriſtianity) to be the By-Blows of the Jeſuits, and Symbolizers with the Papiſts; for which if ye have no better Proof, than that heap of Lies and Slanders which follow, in your Anſwer to the firſt Queſtion, then conſider if Juſtice and Truth do not require you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of your Wickedneſs, and acknowledg you have followed blind Guides to your own hurt, and thereby wronged both your ſelves and your Neighbours?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether we have not by the Word of our Teſtimony in open and publick Aſſemblies, and the many Books ſpread up and down the Nation, ſufficiently clear'd our ſelves from thoſe foul Imputations ye would caſt upon us; ſo that we need not multiply Anſwers to every vain impertinent Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, our Principles and Practice being manifeſt to the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, in the Conſciences of ſober People that know us; which is a Refuge ſufficient for us, againſt ſuch ſilly Blaſts of Envy?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Who is the Man, and where doth he dwell, that dares affirm, he heard <hi>John Whitehead</hi> boaſt of ſuch a Miracle as your 2d Queſtion affirms? That when he was fed in a Priſon with Bread and Water, he fatned on it ſo as that he was <hi>3</hi> yards or more about the Waſte; for I do poſitively deny that ever I made any ſuch boaſt as your Query affirms; and I further ſay, that I was never under thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in a Priſon, as to be confin'd to Bread and VVater; and that I was never of that bigneſs, but that a Girdle of leſs than <hi>4</hi> foot would have met about my VVaſte; and therefore that monstrous prodigious Lie, of my being <hi>3</hi> yards about the VVaſte (there being many hundreds of VVitneſſes to the contrary) is turned back upon you, with that falſe ſuggeſtion, that his Wife is near as ſpacious as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and all thoſe Slanders and ſcornful frothy Inſinuations that follow thereupon, in your Anſwer to your ſecond Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which are as the Smoke of the bottomleſs Pit, and thither muſt deſcend, and into the Lake muſt be caſt all thoſe that love and make Lies, except they repent: Therefore prize your time, and do no more ſo wickedly: This Friendly Admonition is given you by one that can love his Enemies,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Whitehead.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This is his own Letter, which you are deſired to Anſwer; with which I ſhall end, when I have told you, That plain and poſitive Proof muſt make good your Charge, Repentance muſt make you honeſt Men, and the continuance in your Crimes, will make you as Incorrigible as thoſe Beaſts, which ſerve for Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems in your Buffoonry: If you cannot do the firſt, the way to avoid the laſt is by the middlemoſt; which that you may, is the deſire of him who can forgive Enemies, and is in ſcorn call'd a</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Quaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcott</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> 1692. Where the Books above-mentioned are to be had.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
